How are you? Please,
Como você está? Por favor.
What’s your name? REPORTER: My name is David [Cooper?], I am (inaudible)
- Qual é o seu nome? - Meu nome é David (…), eu sou (…).
Can You tell me why You have come along
A Senhora pode me dizer porque veio a Northampton esta semana?
SHRI MATAJI: Why I have come here?
Por que Eu vim aqui?
REPORTER: Why You have come along here were you invited by a....
Por que a Senhora veio aqui? A Senhora foi convidada por um...?
SHRI MATAJI: It’s a sort of a… kind of a message I have,
É um tipo de mensagem que Eu tenho...
that a discovery has been made now of a method.
que a descoberta de um método foi feita agora.
REPORTER: Is this the first time that You’ve come to Northampton?
Esta é a primeira vez que a Senhora vem a Northampton?
SHRI MATAJI: No, I’ve come before also.
Não, Eu vim antes também.
REPORTER: And what sort of response did You get then?
E qual tipo de resposta a Senhora recebeu então?
SHRI MATAJI: Response was, I wouldn’t say very good.
A resposta foi, Eu não diria muito boa.
No newspaper didn’t come at all.
Nenhum jornal veio de forma alguma.
Yesterday also there was no one, it’s very surprising.
Ontem também não havia ninguém, é muito surpreendente.
REPORTER: You found a lot of people were very skeptical, did You?
A Senhora encontrou muitas pessoas que eram muito céticas, não foi?
SHRI MATAJI: I don’t know what they were like,
Eu não sei como eles são, porque ninguém veio.
REPORTER: That was the Guild Hall as well?
Isso aconteceu no Guildhall também?
SHRI MATAJI: No, Guildhall yesterday we had lots of people, yesterday.
Não, no Guildhall ontem, nós tivemos muitas pessoas.
But as far as the newspapers were concerned,
Mas no que se refere aos jornais,
We met some people here.
nós encontramos algumas pessoas aqui.
But most of them came to see Me, when I came here first.
Mas a maioria deles veio Me ver, quando Eu vim aqui primeiro.
They were sort of a labor class people.
Eles eram pessoas da classe trabalhadora.
They were suffering from all kinds of maladies
Eles estavam sofrendo de todos os tipos de doenças...
like possessions and things, and one gentleman just got up
como possessões e coisas assim, e um senhor simplesmente se levantou...
and started walking all around the places and talking like …
e começou a andar por todos os lugares e falar como...
it was a bit funny.
foi um bocado estranho.
REPORTER: In fact, You were in Bedford last night, weren't You?
De fato, a Senhora estava em Bedford na noite passada, não estava?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, I was there.
- Sim, Eu estava lá. - E como foi?
SHRI MATAJI: Very good, very well.
Muito bom, muito bem.
REPORTER: It went very well. In the past, I understand, that You’ve, um,
Foi muito bem. No passado, eu entendo, que a Senhora teve...
You’ve helped heal an awful lot of people? SHRI MATAJI: Yes.
a Senhora ajudou a curar uma quantidade espantosa de pessoas?
REPORTER: Can You give me some examples of some of the more,
A Senhora pode me dar uns exemplos de algumas das mais...
extraordinary healings You’ve done?
extraordinárias curas que a Senhora fez?
SHRI MATAJI: Anything, you see, like cancer.
Qualquer coisa, como por exemplo o câncer.
Then, we can say, blood cancer specially.
Então, podemos dizer, especialmente câncer de sangue.
A Sahaja Yogini has cured one friend's blood cancer.
Uma Sahaja Yogini curou câncer de sangue de um amigo.
Then diabetes.
Depois a diabetes.
REPORTER: In fact, I understand, on one occasion You had
De fato, eu compreendo, em uma ocasião a Senhora tinha...
a blind woman cometo see you, is that right?
uma mulher cega que veio se encontrar com a Senhora, isso está correto?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, blindness — if the eyes are open.
Sim, cegueira, embora os olhos estivessem abertos.
REPORTER: Which one was that exactly? What was happening?
Qual foi exatamente? O que aconteceu?
SHRI MATAJI: That is due to a possession, on the backside,
Aquilo é devido a uma possessão, na parte detrás...
the optic lobe we have here.
do lóbulo ótico que temos aqui.
You see, if that gets possessed by a live entity,
Se essa parte fica possuída por uma entidade viva,
your eyes are open but there’s darkness, you can’t see anything.
seus olhos estão abertos, mas há escuridão, não consegue ver nada.
And if you know how to open that and get rid of the possession…
E se você sabe como abrir isso e livrar-se da possessão...
And the deaf person hearing, yeah…
E a pessoa surda passa a ouvir, sim...
REPORTER: You’ve actually cured deafness as well, have You?
A Senhora na verdade curou a surdez também, não curou?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, I did. There in Geneva it happened.
Sim, Eu curei. Isso aconteceu em Genebra.
REPORTER: Do You — I mean, it’s very difficult for people
É muito dífícil, na verdade, para as pessoas...
to actually understand how it’s done.
entenderem como isso é feito.
I mean they, you know, it all seems just a bit mystical and, you know …
Tudo isso simplesmente parece um bocado místico...
SHRI MATAJI: Yeah. It is nothing mystical, I tell you,
Sim, não é nada místico, Eu lhe digo, não há nada místico.
Like we see a flower becoming a fruit.
Por exemplo, nós vemos uma flor se transformando em um fruto.
We take it for granted, isn’t it?
Não damos o devido valor a isso, não é?
Do we find it mystical ? Because we see it every day.
Nós achamos isso místico? Porque vemos isso todo dia.
But there is something, some power that does that, doesn’t it?
Mas há algo, algum poder que faz isso, não é?
Supposing you become
Vamos supor que você se torne...
the owner of that power, say, or if you have that power within you.
o dono desse poder, ou se você tem esse poder dentro de você,
You can also do many things.
você também pode fazer muitas coisas.
REPORTER: But, nonetheless, I mean,
Mas, todavia, quero dizer, se eu tenho uma doença,
I mean, to actually to come and see You
quero dizer, na verdade, eu vim e me encontrei com a Senhora,
and You say I’ve got the power within me to cure myself…
e a Senhora diz que eu tenho o poder dentro de mim para me curar,
I mean, how do you actually get this power?
como, na verdade, se consegue esse poder?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, what happens: when you become realized,
Veja, o que acontece é que quando você se torna realizado,
or we become — it’s called twice-born —
ou nos tornamos – isso é chamado de duplamente nascido -
then you become collectively conscious, you become.
então você se torna coletivamente consciente, você se torna.
It is not that I just tell you
Não é que Eu simplesmente lhe falo...
and it’s a brain treatment or something,
e é um tratamento cerebral ou algo assim,
or brainwash, that I say,
ou lavagem cerebral, em que Eu falo:
“All right, now you have become this and this.”
“Tudo bem, agora você se tornou isso e aquilo.”
You really become, that you start feeling them —
Você realmente se torna, você começa a senti-los,
they are centres on your fingertips.
eles são centros na ponta de seus dedos.
REPORTER: So you actually feel them? SHRI MATAJI: On the fingertips.
- Então na verdade, você os sente? - Nas pontas dos dedos.
You can, everyone can feel it very clearly.
Você consegue, todos podem sentir isso muito claramente.
REPORTER: So this is like a guide, this is the way to diagnose
Então é como um guia, esse é o meio de diagnosticar.
SHRI MATAJI: Diagnosis. You see, you are the doctor,
Diagnóstico. Você é o médico,
you are the diagnosis, you could be patient also.
você é o diagnóstico, você poderia ser o paciente também.
And you are the medicine.
E você é o remédio.
REPORTER: So once you’ve diagnosed what's wrong…
Então uma vez que você diagnosticou o que está errado...
SHRI MATAJI: Then you should know how to cure a particular centre.
Então você deve saber como curar um determinado centro.
For example, now, which is the Christ centre? It’s this one.
Por exemplo, agora, qual é o centro de Cristo? É este aqui.
These two are Christ centres,
Estes dois são centros de Cristo, na glândula pituitária e pineal.
All the diseases of the eyes you get out of it.
Você se livra de todas as doenças dos olhos. Outras são possessões.
You see, people are mentally depressed, this, that —
Veja, as pessoas estão mentalmente deprimidas, isso, aquilo,
all this is due to the problem of this centre.
tudo isso é por causa do problema deste centro.
There could be ego problems also.
Poderia haver problemas de ego também.
People are egoistical, you see, and very bombastic,
As pessoas são egoístas e são muito enfáticas,
and they try to destroy others with their ego.
e elas tentam destruir os outros com o ego delas.
All these problems can be solved if you can awaken Christ within you.
Todos esses problemas podem ser resolvidos,
Because it’s said that He died for our sins.
Porque é dito que Ele morreu pelos nossos pecados.
REPORTER: And using this healing method You've got, that actually awakens powers [of healing]
E usando esse método de cura que a Senhora obteve,
SHRI MATAJI: Yes. You just have to say Lord's prayer before Me
Sim, você apenas tem de recitar o Pai Nosso diante de Mim...
and He awakens because I am connected with Him, you see.
e Ele desperta, porque Eu estou conectada com Ele.
So when you say something to Me,
Então quando você diz algo para Mim,
that connection is just made, and that is awakened,
essa conexão simplesmente é feita, e isso é despertado,
and there is ego and superego in your head, which are sucked in,
e há ego e superego em sua cabeça, que são absorvidos,
means your actions — that is your karmas —
significa que suas ações, isto é, seus karmas...
and your sins all are sucked in.
e todos seus pecados são absorvidos.
Once they are sucked in, this portion opens up.
Uma vez que eles sejam absorvidos, essa parte se abre.
When this opens up, you get the the Kundalini up.
Quando isto se abre, você levanta a Kundalini.
That is, it’s very simple, you know, because it’s all done.
Isto é, é muito simples, porque está tudo pronto.
For example, now look at this. To look at this, looks very simple,
Por exemplo, agora olhe para isto.
but it might be quite complicated inside.
mas pode ser muito complicado interiormente.
And it has taken years to make it.
E levou anos para formar isso.
So the whole thing has taken ages to make it. This human body
Assim, a coisa toda levou séculos para formar isso.
even from matter to this stage. All that is built within you.
até mesmo da matéria a este estágio.
Not only that, but what is going to happen to you
Não somente isso, mas o que vai lhe acontecer...
is also existing within you in your heart; the Spirit.
também existe dentro de você em seu coração; o Espírito.
Now, only thing, that last [ ] breakthrough has to take place.
Agora, a única coisa é que esse grande avanço tem de acontecer.
That is also built within you, that is sahaja —
Isso também está construído dentro de você, isso é sahaja,
means built within you. It is born within you.
significa “construído dentro de você, nascido dentro de você.”
Sahaja is “born within”. So it’s all within you.
“Sahaja” é “nascido com”. Assim, tudo está dentro de você.
And just if somebody knows how to do the job,
E se simplesmente alguém sabe como fazer o trabalho,
the one who could have capacity…
aquele que poderia ter a capacidade...
Like the Mother Earth has the capacity to sprout the seed.
assim como a Mãe Terra tem a capacidade de germinar a semente.
We can’t do it otherwise, if you do grow, do anything, you can't.
Não conseguimos fazer isso, se você de fato cultivá-la,
It’s a living process. But the Mother… Mother Earth can help.
É um processo vivo. Mas a Mãe, a Mãe Terra pode ajudar.
You put it there and you get it.
Você a coloca lá e consegue isso.
In the same way, it is supposing I have the capacity, I can do it.
Da mesma maneira, supondo que Eu tenha a capacidade, Eu posso fazê-lo.
Supposing you get the light tomorrow, you can do it.
Supondo que você alcance a iluminação amanhã, você pode fazê-lo.
You can enlighten another person.
Você pode iluminar uma outra pessoa.
One enlightened person can enlighten another person
Uma pessoa iluminada pode iluminar uma outra pessoa,
but he has to be enlightened first of all.
mas ela tem de ser iluminada antes de tudo.
REPORTER: Do You find that, I mean, as You say, I mean,
A Senhora acha que, como a Senhora diz,
once people have seen You and discovered how it can work,
quando as pessoas A viram e descobriram como isso pode funcionar,
they can spread the word? SHRI MATAJI: Yes.
- elas podem espalhar a notícia? - Sim.
REPORTER: But nonetheless You say You met a lot of skeptical people last time.
Mas a Senhora diz que se encontrou com muitas pessoas céticas...
Do You think that that is the basic problem I mean that…
da última vez. A Senhora acha que esse é o problema básico que...
through this healing process You have
através desse processo de cura que a Senhora tem...
could be much more widely used and sort of...
poderia ser muito mais amplamente usado e um tipo de...
SHRI MATAJI: You see, but I’ve seen people who come for healing,
Veja, mas Eu tenho visto pessoas que vêm pela cura,
just get satisfied at that point when they are healed up.
simplesmente ficam satisfeitas nesse ponto quando elas são curadas.
They don’t go further.
Elas não vão além. Você deve dizer que Deus também tem bom senso,
that He would like to only heal people, normally,
que Ele gostaria de curar somente as pessoas que normalmente...
like we would like to only construct,
emitirão luzes, assim como gostaríamos somente de construir,
improve, or repair those lamps which will give lights, isn’t it?
de melhorar, de reparar estas lâmpadas, não é?
So those who are not going to work it out;
Assim, com aqueles que não vão trabalhar isso, o interesse é menor.
But still it works, I mean, it’s compassion,
Mas ainda assim funciona, é a compaixão,
so it cures, people get cured, no doubt.
então ela cura, as pessoas ficam curadas, sem dúvida. Mas dentre eles,
But out of them I find very few really come to Sahaja Yoga,
Eu percebo que muito poucos realmente vêm para a Sahaja Yoga,
who come through healing. But those who have seeking of the Spirit
que vêm através da cura. Mas aqueles que têm buscado o Espírito,
they are a special category of people.
eles são uma categoria especial de pessoas.
They are extremely beautiful people
Eles são pessoas extremamente belas...
and they are seeking. Maybe they are taking drugs,
e estão buscando. Talvez eles estejam tomando drogas,
going to wrong gurus, whatever they are doing.
indo a falsos gurus, seja o que for que estejam fazendo.
That’s a different point.
Isso é um ponto diferente.
But they are seekers, basically they are seekers of the truth
Mas eles são buscadores, basicamente eles são buscadores da verdade...
and they are the best people.
e eles são as melhores pessoas.
And they are the ones who are meant for Sahaja Yoga,
E eles são os que estão destinados à Sahaja Yoga,
not the people who just want their body to be all right.
não as pessoas que só querem que seu corpo fique bem.
What’s the use of having the body, what are you going to do with it?
De que adianta ter o corpo? O que você vai fazer com ele?
You see, this body might have a meaning.
Talvez este corpo tenha um significado.
And those who are finding the meaning are the best helped.
E aqueles que estão descobrindo o significado são os mais ajudados.
Of course, they get rid of all their maladies
É claro, eles se livram de todas as doenças...
and everything that’s… as a by-product.
e tudo mais, isso é como um subproduto.
But that’s the main thing, that’s important.
Mas aquilo é a coisa principal, aquilo é importante.
REPORTER: I understand that Your husband, in fact,
Eu entendo que Seu marido, de fato,
holds a very eminent position. SHRI MATAJI: Yes, he is.
- possui um cargo muito elevado. - Sim, ele tem.
REPORTER: Can You tell me a little bit about that?
A Senhora pode me falar um pouco sobre isso?
SHRI MATAJI: He is elected as Secretary General.
Ele foi nomeado como Secretário Geral.
REPORTER: Of what exactly?
Do que exatamente?
SHRI MATAJI: Of one international organization you have,
De uma organização internacional que vocês têm,
a one agency you have in this country,
uma agência que vocês têm neste país,
called as International Maritime Organization,
chamada de Organização Marítima Internacional,
which has got 134 nations
a qual é composta de 134 nações...
who have elected him. And that’s how we are here.
que o elegeram. E é desse modo que estamos aqui.
REPORTER: Do You find… I mean, his work
A Senhora acha, quero dizer, o trabalho dele...
must be so completely different to Yours.
deve ser completamente diferente do da Senhora.
SHRI MATAJI: No, it’s quite just the same, I feel,
Não, é quase a mesma coisa, Eu acho,
because My work only works out how I meet people, isn’t it?
porque Meu trabalho só funciona porque encontro as pessoas, não é?
And when I meet the people, I find they like My work.
E quando encontro as pessoas, percebo que elas gostam de Meu trabalho.
I help his people also sometimes, you can say,
Eu ajudo o pessoal dele às vezes também, você pode dizer,
for something wrong with them.
por causa de algo errado com eles.
But it never collides with My work at all, I find,
Mas isso nunca colide com Meu trabalho, de forma alguma, Eu acho,
because you are so…
porque vocês são tão...
you become so loving and affectionate and so tolerant
vocês se tornam tão amorosos e efetuosos e tão tolerantes...
that you just don’t feel anything else.
que você simplesmente não sente nada mais.
It’s very nice to meet new people because…
É muito bom encontrar novas pessoas, porque...
Because of him I’ve gone to many communist countries,
Por causa dele, Eu fui a muitos países comunistas,
I visited China and visited Russia…
Eu visitei a China e visitei a Rússia.
All these places I could not have visited.
Todos esses lugares, Eu não poderia ter visitado.
REPORTER: I think, um…
Eu acho...
I mean, You must have a great deal of difficulty
A Senhora deve ter muitas difículdades para convencer...
person, You know, it’s a little bit dangerous.
é um pouco perigoso.
Do You find that there is, um, problems with people who are
A Senhora acha que há problemas com as pessoas que são...
extreme, sort of extreme people who are... ?
extremadas, tipos de pessoas extremadas que são...?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, it depends on what country you are.
Veja, depende de qual país você está.
Say, in India it’s not difficult at all, because they understand this,
Na Índia, não é dífícil de forma alguma, porque compreendem isso.
They know, they have had an education on this,
Eles sabem, eles tiveram uma educação nisso,
that the one who awakens the Kundalini is the real person.
que uma pessoa que desperta a Kundalini é uma pessoa genuína.
You see, they can see the rising of the Kundalini,
Eles conseguem ver a elevação da Kundalini,
they can see the pulsation of the Kundalini,
eles conseguem ver a pulsação
they can feel the pulsation here.
eles conseguem sentir a pulsação aqui.
It’s all told them, so they know about it.
Tudo isso lhes é falado, então eles sabem sobre isso.
I don’t have to work out with them.
Eu não tenho de trabalhar com eles. Mas por outro lado,
most of the seekers in other countries also have
a maioria dos buscadores em outros países também...
come to right conclusions, because they have had a very bad time.
chegaram às conclusões corretas, porque tiveram um momento muito ruim.
So they have come to right conclusions, I mean it’s not so difficult.
Assim, eles chegaram às conclusões corretas, não é tão dífícil.
But of course, you know,
Mas é claro, se há muita projeção mental, então é muito dífícil.
But it doesn’t matter.
Mas isso não importa.
REPORTER: Are there fakes in this country?
- Há impostores neste país? - Muitos, a maioria deles são.
REPORTER: I mean, they must be Your biggest headache,
Eles devem ser a sua maior dor de cabeça, eu acho, talvez.
SHRI MATAJI: They are not only Mine but of all the seekers.
Eles não são somente Minha dor de cabeça, mas de todos os buscadores.
And that’s very true.
E isso é verdade. Eles realmente arruínam os buscadores.
put these people out of jobs, out of their lives,
fazem essas pessoas saírem dos empregos, saírem de suas vidas,
make them abnormal, sick like cabbages,
tornam-nas anormais, doentes como pessoas tolas,
they take away… the children are ruined…it's horrible.
eles retiram... as crianças ficam arruinadas, é horrível.
Some of them get epilepsy, some of them get cancer…
Alguns deles contraem epilepsia, alguns deles contraem câncer,
all kinds of diseases. Some people become blind.
todos os tipos de doenças. Algumas pessoas ficam cegas.
They all punish them-
Todos eles os punem.
REPORTER: You don’t in fact charge anything, do You?
A Senhora de fato não cobra nada, cobra?
SHRI MATAJI: No no no. No no.
Não, não, não. Não, não.
REPORTER: Then how is, Your trips round the country,
Então como são feitas Suas viagens pelo país,
to different countries and around Britain and so on,
para diferentes países e pela Inglaterra e etc,
how are they actually funded then?
como elas são, na verdade, financiadas?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, it is mostly funded by My husband.
A maioria delas é financiada pelo Meu marido.
Mostly he’s a generous man.
A maioria, ele é um homem generoso.
REPORTER: That’s lucky, isn’t it!
Que sorte, não é?
SHRI MATAJI: He’s generous.
Ele é generoso.
Otherwise also I have My some income of My own.
Por outro lado também, Eu tenho Minha própria renda.
REPORTER: How much would You estimate
Quanto a Senhora estimaria...
that You spend trying to spread the word, a year?
que a Senhora gasta tentando divulgar Seus ensinamentos por ano?
SHRI MATAJI: Well, I can't say that, I’m not good at accounting,
Bem, Eu não consigo dizer, não sou boa em contabilidade,
but I would say that when I travel,
mas Eu diria que quando Eu viajo,
for example, supposing I go to any other country,
por exemplo, vamos supor que Eu vá para algum outro país,
sometimes Sahaja Yogis think that I should not pay
às vezes os Sahaja Yogis acham que Eu não deveria pagar...
for their salvation, you see.
pela salvação deles.
So out of their self-respect they pay My traveling sometimes,
Então por autorrespeito, eles pagam Minha viagem às vezes,
but they don’t pay Me but to the travel agency or something they,
mas não Me pagam, pagam apenas para a agência de viagem ou algo assim,
buy tickets for Me at the most, that’s all.
no máximo compram as passagens para Mim, só isso.
But not much, it’s not much per year.
Mas não muito, não é muito por ano.
REPORTER: Where have You traveled this year?
Para onde a Senhora viajou este ano?
SHRI MATAJI: Now, this year, let’s start.
Agora, este ano, vamos ver.
When… where did I go, can you…?
Quando... aonde Eu fui, você pode...?
Now, I came from America…
Agora, Eu vim dos Estados Unidos.
Geneva, Austria, Belgium,
Fui a Genebra, Áustria, Bélgica, Espanha, Portugal, França,
Germany… Russia, I went to Russia, Uzbekistan.
Alemanha, Rússia, Eu fui à Rússia, Uzbequistão.
REPORTER: And this is all this year, is it?
E tudo isso este ano, não é?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, this year, yes... REPORTER: You must be worn out.
- Sim, este ano, sim -  A Senhora deve estar esgotada.
SHRI MATAJI: Do I look that? Now I’m sixty. I’m sixty now.
Eu pareço? Agora Eu tenho 60 anos, tenho 60 anos agora.
REPORTER: Really? SHRI MATAJI: Yes, I'm sixty years of age, really.
Sim, Eu tenho 60 anos de idade, é verdade.
REPORTER: You don’t look sixty years old at all.
A Senhora não parece ter 60 anos de forma alguma.
REPORTER: How did it all start for You then,
Como tudo isso começou para a Senhora? Desde o começo.
Well, say, I mean, most people know very little
Bem, a maioria das pessoas sabem muito pouco...
about this sort of thing, me included.
sobre esse tipo de coisa, inclusive eu.
But how did that actually all start in the beginning for You?
Mas como isso tudo realmente começou para a Senhora?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, actually I was aware of it
Na verdade, Eu estava consciente disso...
from My very childhood, as you are aware, say, for example,
desde Minha infância, assim como você está consciente, por exemplo,
you are aware you are a human being. In the same way I was aware.
você está consciente de que é um ser humano. Da mesma maneira,
I was absolutely aware of Me, and My mission,
Eu estava totalmente consciente de Mim, e de Minha missão,
and what I… why I’m here, what I am.
e porque Eu estou aqui, quem Eu sou.
Everything  I was aware of from My very childhood.
Eu estava consciente desde a Minha infância.
But I was working out how to do it in en masse happening.
Mas Eu estava resolvendo como fazer isso em um acontecimento em massa.
It would be for the masses.
Isso seria para as massas.
My father himself was a realized soul
Meu próprio pai era uma alma realizada...
and he was a member of the Parliament and Assembly in those days,
e ele era membro do Parlamento e da Assembléia naquela época,
and he was the only Indian to be elected.
e ele era o único indiano eleito.
Indian Christian to be elected, I should say.
Indiano cristão eleito, Eu devo dizer.
My brother also is a Minister of… what is he Minister of?
Meu irmão também era um ministro – ele era ministro de quê?
Communications and something else.
Comunicações e alguma outra coisa.
REPORTER: So, I mean, I suppose in India,
Eu suponho que na Índia, não é dífícil,
It’s only when You start traveling abroad?
Isso aconteceu somente quando Você começou a viajar para o exterior?
SHRI MATAJI: Oh, Indians understand much better.
Oh, os indianos compreendem muito melhor.
REPORTER: That’s what I was saying.
Isso é o que eu estava dizendo.
SHRI MATAJI: But abroad is the problem. Because, you see, they…
Mas fora do país é o problema. Porque eles...
they are naive, they don’t know.
eles são ingênuos, eles não sabem.
You see, Christ’s life was only for four years.
A vida de Cristo foi somente por quatro anos.
He couldn’t tell them much about it; about the Holy Ghost.
Ele não pode lhes falar muito sobre isso; sobre o Espírito Santo.
It’s all a mystery, you see.
É tudo um mistério.
The Christianity could not give that, because they never went
O Cristianismo não pôde proporcionar isso, porque eles nunca...
into the search of it, you see, the deeper of it.
penetraram na busca disso, no mais profundo disso.
Just reading Bible, telling some sort of an interpretation
Apenas lendo a Bíblia, falando algum tipo de interpretação...
doesn’t give you anything.
não lhes propicia nada.
So the second birth part of it they didn’t work out.
Assim, a parte relativa ao segundo nascimento, eles não trabalharam.
And that’s why I find people got lost more,
E é por isso que Eu percebo que as pessoas se perderam mais,
because of these gurus coming, giving them some ideas, this, that…
por causa desses gurus vindo, lhes dando algumas ideias, isso, aquilo.
And they sort of are hypnotized also to a great extent.
E eles ficam meio que hipnotizados também em grande escala.
All these people are hypnotized, brainwashed,
Todas essas pessoas são hipnotizadas, sofrem lavagem cerebral,
then they, some of them went into drugs.
então elas, algumas delas recorreram às drogas.
You see, so many things, they are all self-destroying.
Tantas coisas, todas elas estão se autodestruindo.
That’s how I found people very much confused, very much confused.
É desse modo que percebi as pessoas muito confusas, muito confusas.
Of course, the people in India
É claro, as pessoas na Índia, por exemplo, este empreendedor,
He knows I am a saint.
ele sabe que Eu sou uma santa.
So he treats Me like a saint, it’s a very big thing,
Então ele Me trata como uma santa, é uma coisa muito grande,
and then he'll come to receive Me and…
e depois ele virá para Me receber e...
that even the Prime Minister of India,
até mesmo o Primeiro Ministro da Índia,
Mr. Lal Bahadur Shastri,  My husband was his secretary,
Mr. Lal Bahadur Shastri, Meu marido foi seu secretário,
but he used to come and see Me often, in the car, you see.
mas ele costumava vir e Me ver com frequência, no carro.
So in India it’s a… saint is higher than all kings
Assim, na Índia, um santo é mais elevado do que todos os reis...
and everyone put together, you see.
e todos juntos.
So they know how to respect a saint, even for popularity.
Eles sabem como respeitar um santo, mesmo por popularidade.
REPORTER: Do You find that, I mean… to call Yourself a saint…
A Senhora acha que, quero dizer, chamar-se de santa...
do You find that the people in England…
A Senhora acha que as pessoas na Inglaterra...
SHRI MATAJI: They are not so much.
- Eles não são tanto desse jeito. - Eles não são muito perspicazes...
SHRI MATAJI: (unclear...) the saints, I think.
(…) os santos, Eu acho.
No, they care more for politicians.
Não, eles se interessam mais por políticos.
REPORTER: That’s right, that’s right.
Isso está correto, isso está correto. A Senhora acha que...
I mean, You are little bit insulted by them sometimes?
a Senhora é um pouco insultada por eles às vezes?
SHRI MATAJI: Aah, it’s all right.
Ahh, tudo bem.
REPORTER: I mean, You firmly believe in what You do, obviously, and
A Senhora acredita firmemente no que faz obviamente,
it must seem incredible to You when other people [ignore?] it.
deve ser inacreditável para Senhora quando outras pessoas ignoram isso.
SHRI MATAJI: It’s all right. You see, after all they are children,
Tudo bem, afinal todos eles são crianças,
they don’t understand. That’s all I can say.
eles não compreendem. Isso é tudo que posso dizer.
Because they are still children in spiritual life, you see.
Porque eles ainda são crianças na vida espiritual.
But they are not going to crucify Me this time, isn’t it?
Mas eles não irão Me crucificar desta vez, não é?
So it’s all right.
Então está tudo bem.
REPORTER: Now, when You make these trips
Agora, quando a Senhora faz essas viagens...
to towns like Northampton and so on,
a cidades como Northampton e etc,
You got several people with You.
a Senhora tem muitas pessoas com Você.
Does this team come with You every time?
Essa equipe vai com a Senhora o tempo todo?
SHRI MATAJI: No, they are from this place, some of them are now
Não, eles são deste lugar, alguns deles estão agora...
and some of them are there also. Of course all the others
e alguns deles estão presentes também. É claro, todos os outros...
they have come from Australia.
vieram da Austrália.
And we have an ashram in South London.
E nós temos um ashram no sul de Londres.
So they are staying there, so they just came around here.
Então eles estão ficando lá, eles simplesmente aparecem por aqui.
And these two are from -
E estes dois são de -
he’s working in London, he is also there.
ele está trabalhando em Londres, ele também vive lá.
And these three gentlemen are from Bedford. He is from Bristol.
E estes três cavalheiros são de Bedford. Ele é de Bristol.
REPORTER: Oh I see. SHRI MATAJI: But there is nothing like that,
- Entendo. - Mas não há nada como...
is that a team or anything.
uma equipe ou qualquer coisa assim.
Anybody who feels like can come around if they’re free, because…
Qualquer um que tem vontade aparece, se estiverem livres, porque...
REPORTER: So anyone who is available for You, to help…
Qualquer um que esteja disponível para Senhora, para ajudar...
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, they can just to help Me,
Sim, eles podem simplesmente Me ajudar,
because if it’s a big group and all that, so they can help Me.
porque se é um grupo grande e tudo mais, então eles podem Me ajudar.
REPORTER: I see, all right, I see.
Entendo, tudo bem, entendo. Bem, muito obrigado pelo Seu tempo.
SHRI MATAJI: Thank you very much. But I think you should ask
Muito obrigada. Mas Eu acho que você deveria fazer...
one more question if you can, say, about Kundalini,
mais uma pergunta, se você puder, sobre a Kundalini,
because those who have read about Kundalini
porque aqueles que leram sobre a Kundalini...
would be interested to know.
estariam interessados em saber.
Is that, is said that, you see, lots of books
É que é dito, muitos livros foram escritos sobre a Kundalini,
that it’s very dangerous, it is very (this thing?), and all that.
em que é dito que é muito perigosa, que Ela é muito (…) e tudo mais.
But it is not at all.
Mas Ela não é de forma alguma.
You see, thousands of people I’ve given realization. Thousands.
Veja, Eu dei a Realização a milhares de pessoas. Milhares.
It has never put anybody into danger at all.
Isso nunca colocou ninguém em perigo de forma alguma.
But those who are naïve, those who are unholy persons,
Mas aqueles que são ingênuos, aqueles que não são pessoas santas,
who have no idea of a spiritual life, you see,
que não têm nenhuma ideia sobre uma vida espiritual,
if they try tricks, you see,
se eles tentam truques,
like sex, you see, through sex and all that nonsense,
como sexo, através do sexo e toda essa insensatez,
then it feels insulted, and then there are problems.
então Ela se sente insultada e então há problemas.
REPORTER: How can it be dangerous then?
Repórter: Então como isso pode ser perigoso?
SHRI MATAJI: Beg your pardon? REPORTER: How, You said, it can be dangerous
- Perdão - Repórter: Como a Senhora disse, isso pode ser perigoso,
if it's not used properly?
se não for usado apropriadamente?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, like we could say that
Por exemplo, nós poderíamos dizer que...
if I don’t know this instrument and I put My hand into something,
se Eu não conheço este instrumento e coloco Minha mão em alguma coisa,
I may get a burning, but it doesn’t mean this is dangerous,
Eu posso Me queimar, mas não significa que isso é perigoso,
that is because I don’t know how to work it…
é perigoso porque Eu não sei como lidar com ele.
REPORTER:That is basic, I mean, if you don’t understand it's
Repórter: Isto é básico, se você não entende,
like putting your finger in an electric light socket...…
é como colocar seu dedo no soquete da luz elétrica.
SHRI MATAJI: That’s what, you see. That’s like that, you see.
Isso é o que acontece. É desse jeito.
But they try to do it
Mas eles tentam fazer isso...
and then they try to write books about it.
e depois tentam escrever livros sobre isso.
It’s something surprising, isn’t it?
É algo surpreendente, não é?
I haven’t written any book so far.
Eu não escrevi nenhum livro até agora.
REPORTER: So, that’s obviously, You know,
Então isso é, obviamente, um tipo de coisa que...
sort of the thing you've got to try and make clear to people.
você tem de experimentar e se torna claro para as pessoas.
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, you have to. And then, you see,
Sim, você tem de experimentar. E depois,
when you get realization, you automatically become righteous,
quando você obtém a Realização, você automaticamente se torna correto,
I don’t have to tell you “Become righteous.”
Eu não tenho de lhe dizer: “Torne-se correto.”
Because the religion is enlightened within you.
Porque a religião é iluminada dentro de você.
You automatically become. I don’t tell you that “You don’t drink,”
Você automaticamente se torna. Eu não tenho de lhe dizer: “Não beba”,
you just don’t drink, because you don’t enjoy it any more.
você simplesmente não bebe, porque você não gosta mais disso.
You don’t smoke, because you just don’t enjoy it; don’t take drugs.
Você não fuma, porque simplesmente não gosta disso, não toma drogas.
Just you just don’t do it because it’s all enlightened,
Você simplesmente não faz isso, porque tudo está iluminado,
because a new priority has come.
porque uma nova prioridade surgiu.
Like if there’s light in this room, suddenly you start seeing
Por exemplo, se há luz nesta sala, de repente você começa a ver...
where’s the position of everything,
onde está a posição de tudo,
and you know, if you walk this way, you’ll be hit.
e você sabe que se andar por este caminho, você se machucará.
In the same way, enlightenment means that
Da mesma maneira, a iluminação significa que...
automatically you become righteous.
automaticamente você se torna correto.
REPORTER: What is Your success rate in full for healing people?
Repórter: Qual é a Sua taxa de sucesso no total em curar pessoas?
SHRI MATAJI: What is?… REPORTER: What is Your success rate
- O quê? - Qual é a Sua traxa de sucesso...
for healing people who come to see You?
em curar pessoas que vêm vê-La?
SHRI MATAJI: Success? REPORTER: Successful or have helped them.
- Sucesso? - É  bem sucedida ou as ajudou.
REPORTER: How many times do You actually heal people
Quantas vezes a Senhora realmente curou pessoas...
compared to the number of people who come to see You?
comparado ao número de pessoas que vêm vê-La?
SHRI MATAJI: Oh, some people just come, for ten minutes is sufficient.
Algumas pessoas só vêm por dez minuros, é o suficiente.
Our president Sanjiva Reddy, the first president,
Nosso presidente Sanjuva Reddy, o primeiro presidente,
he was coming from England… America.
ele estava vindo da Inglaterra – dos Estados Unidos.
His operation had failed, he was just in a very bad shape.
A operação dele foi malsucedida, ele estava com um aspecto muito ruim.
I just went to see him
Eu apenas fui vê-lo e ele não sabia que...
And suddenly our High Commissioner told him,
E de repente nosso Alto Comissário lhe disse:
“This is Mataji Nirmala Devi.”
“Esta é Mataji Nirmala Devi.”
So his wife said, “I’ve heard You have cured so many people,
Sua esposa disse: “Eu ouvi falar que a Senhora curou muitas pessoas,”
so just cure my husband.”
“então apenas cure meu marido.”
I put My hand only for ten minutes, you’ll be surprised.
Eu coloquei Minha mão só por dez minutos, você ficará surpreso.
He was just, then — he got it.
Ele só estava lá, então ele conseguiu.
REPORTER: This can happen every time
Repórter: Isso pode acontecer toda vez...
when You get somebody come to see You?
que a Senhora recebe alguém para vê-La?
SHRI MATAJI: Not always. Some people take more time,
Não sempre. Algumas pessoas levam mais tempo,
some people take less time.
algumas pessoas levam menos tempo.
It depends on if they are complicated,
Depende, se eles são complicados,
you see, they take more time, some of them do.
eles levam mais tempo, alguns deles levam.
You see, for example, supposing I have to break through, now.
Por exemplo, vamos supor que Eu tenha de alcançar êxito agora,
And if you are just there, you will out.
e se você simplemente estiver lá, você revelará.
REPORTER: Are there some people You just simply can’t heal?
Há algumas pessoas que a Senhora simplesmente não consegue curar?
SHRI MATAJI: Some people… I don’t know, but, you see…
Algumas pessoas – Eu não sei, mas veja...
I don’t know, I don’t remember of someone
Eu não sei, não Me lembro de ninguém...
who came to Me and was not healed so far.
que veio a Mim e não foi curada, até o momento.
Some might have been, I don’t know.
Algumas pessoas talvez, Eu não sei.
But those who came, you see, assiduously —
Mas aqueles que vieram, assiduamente -
I don’t think, isn’t it?
Eu acho que não, não é? Até onde Me lembro, Eu devo dizer.
REPORTER: Yeah, You've done quite a lot.
Sim, a Senhora fez muito.
SHRI MATAJI: You see, there are so many I have, it has happened,
Há muitos que Eu curei, isso aconteceu,
even these people are healing, you see.
curei até mesmo essas pessoas que estão curando.
So there’s no end to it. Imagine,
Então não há fim para isso. Imagine,
one person is Me, I can remember for Myself,
Eu sou uma única pessoa, Eu mesma consigo Me lembrar,
but there are so many they are healing, and
mas há muitos que estão curando,
I just forget about it, I just don’t remember.
e Eu simplesmente esqueço isso, simplesmente não Me lembro.
Once I had gone to a program, I was just sitting.
Uma vez Eu fui a um programa, Eu estava apenas sentada.
One gentleman came, he just touched My feet.
Um senhor veio, ele simplesmente tocou Meus pés.
I said, “Who are you?” He said, “You forgot me?”
Eu disse: “Quem é você?” Ele disse: “A Senhora se esqueceu de mim?”
I said, “Why?” I said, “I’m sorry.”
Eu disse: “Por quê?” Eu disse: “Sinto muito.”
He said, “I’m the father of such and such girl,
Ele disse: “Eu sou o pai de tal garota...”
whom You cured in two minutes time,
“que a Senhora curou em dois minutos,”
who was going to die, and this and that in the hospital.”
“que ia morrer no hospital.” Eu disse: “Verdade?”
I tried to remember, I said, “Who was this?” you see.
Eu tentei Me lembrar, Eu disse: “Quem era ela?”
Then with very great difficulty I remembered,
Então com difículdade muito grande, Eu Me lembrei,
because it was so quick.
porque foi tão rápido.
I had gone to see somebody else
Eu tinha ido ver uma outra pessoa e na volta, ele Me segurou.
And there she was. She was cured in such a quick manner
E lá estava ela. Ela foi curada de uma forma tão rápida...
that I'd forgotten all about it. REPORTER: Really?
- que Eu esqueci totalmente disso. -  Verdade?
Well, I suppose, the proof is in the pudding, isn’t it?
Bem, eu imagino que a prova está nos resultados, não é?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes. And moreover, what I’m saying
Sim. E além do mais, o que Eu estou dizendo...
it is not important. What is important is to become Spirit.
não é importante. O que é importante é se tornar o Espírito.
Healing is not important.
A cura não é importante.
You see, because everyone has to die in any case, isn’t it?
Porque tudo mundo tem de morrer de qualquer maneira, não é?
What is important  that you have to become the Spirit.
O que é importante é que você tem de se tornar o Espírito.
That is. And then you heal others.
Isso é importante. E então você cura os outros.
Not only yourself, you can heal yourself and heal others also.
Não somente você mesmo, você pode se curar e curar os outros também.
REPORTER: All right, very good... Well, as I say,
Repórter: Tudo bem, muito bom. Bem como eu disse,
thank You, thank You for Your time.
obrigado, obrigado pelo Seu tempo.
SHRI MATAJI: Many incurable diseases you can put,
Você pode aplicar isso a muitas doenças incuráveis,
but that’s not the main job, I think.
mas esse não é o trabalho principal, Eu acho.
REPORTER: Yes. I think that’s probably the thing
Repórter: Sim, eu acho que essa é, provavelmente, a coisa...
that a lot of people are most interested in.
na qual muitas pessoas estão mais interessadas.
SHRI MATAJI: I agree, yes. YOGI: Excuse me, Mother.
Eu concordo, sim.
but they described Her as a man.
mas eles A descreveram como um homem.
[YOGINI SPEAKING]
[Yogini falando]
SHRI MATAJI: What is she…
O que ela é...
REPORTER: I think you are speaking to the wrong person.
Repórter: Eu acho que você está falando para a pessoa errada.
YOGI: I’m getting confused.
Yogi: Estou ficando confuso.
SHRI MATAJI: What is it? What is it?
O que é? O que é?
[YOGINI SPEAKING]
[Yogini falando]
SHRI MATAJI: Yeah. REPORTER: This is in fact…
- Sim - Repórter: Isto de fato...
SHRI MATAJI: Ah, I remember that.
Ah, Me lembro disso.
And he also said I’m a He, you see, put My photograph.
E ele também disse que Eu sou Ele, colocou Minha fotografia.
And they referred to Me as a He, you see, [UNCLEAR].
E eles se referiram a Mim como Ele, veja. (…)
REPORTER: In fact, this would be the first article we've ever run on You, so....
De fato, este seria o primeiro artigo que realizamos com a Senhora.
(Yogi apologizing)SHRI MATAJI: This is [unclear].
[Yogi se desculpando) Isto é (…)
REPORTER: That’s all right, that’s all right.
Repórter: Tudo bem, tudo bem.
It often happens, actually.
Isso acontece com frequência, na verdade.
SHRI MATAJI: It happens. I’ve seen, there have been
Isso acontece. Eu tenho visto, tem havido...
so many things - like Me, also, as you said, I am just…
muitas coisas, como Eu também, como você disse, Eu só estou...
sometimes I don’t remember all… REPORTER: That’s right.
- às vezes Eu não Me lembro de tudo. - Repórter: Isso está correto.
SHRI MATAJI: All right. So…
Tudo bem. Então...
REPORTER: Can I take just two more pictures?
Repórter: Eu posso tirar mais duas fotografias?
SHRI MATAJI: Yes yes, please, please go ahead.
Sim, sim, por favor, por favor, vá em frente.
PHOTOGRAPHER: Actually, if You could close Your hands,
Fotógrafo: Na verdade, se a Senhora pudesse fechar Suas mãos,
so… You know, which is normally…do you mind if I move this?
que normalmente é... a Senhora se importa se eu mover isto?
SHRI MATAJI: As you say. REPORTER: Sometimes a problem.
- Como você diz. - Às vezes há um problema.
SHRI MATAJI: Our style is like this. Is this all right?
Nosso estilo é assim. Tudo bem?
SHRI MATAJI: You can ask
Você pode pedir...
to put their hands towards My photograph also.
para colocar as mãos deles em direção à Minha fotografia também.
My photograph has vibrations.
Minha fotografia tem vibrações.
You see, they have got realization from My photograph.
Eles tiveram a Realização com Minha fotografia.
Yes, really, they have been cured from My photograph.
Sim, realmente, eles têm sido curados com Minha fotografia.
REPORTER: That’s incredible, isn’t it? SHRI MATAJI: Yes, that's it,
- Repórter: Isso é incrível, não é? - Sim, é isso mesmo.
That’s what I was speaking, it's going to help,
Isso é o que Eu estava falando, irá ajudar,
Sahaj is going to help all of them.
a Sahaja irá ajudar todos eles.
REPORTER: So the more of them we get, a thousand more pictures we have…
Então quanto mais delas conseguirmos, mais 1000 fotos que tenhamos...
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, the pictures. These people (unclear)
Sim, as fotos. Essas pessoas (…)
something like [unclear] photograph.
algo como (…) fotografia.
Not only as photograph but just cure people, we have seen.
Não somente como uma fotografia, mas cura pessoas, nós temos visto.
And first time I went to Australia,
E na primeira vez que fui à Austrália,
there was big  [unclear]
havia um grande (…).
What happened, that a relation of a very big man in that industry
O que aconteceu é que um parente de um homem importante na indústria...
was [unclear].
Era (…)
And a lady, one of the Sahaja Yoginis,
E uma senhora, uma das Sahaja Yoginis,
so she said that, “I can’t (...unclear...),
então ela disse: “Eu não posso (…),”
so let's put a photograph" and (unclear).
“então vamos colocar uma fotografia” e (…)
[UNCLEAR]
(…)
Not only that, not only that,
Não somente isso, não somente isso,
but the patient (unclear, was perfectly all right?)
mas o paciente ficou perfeitamente bem.
And that’s how they gave it and that’s how
E é desse modo que eles a deram e é desse modo...
the photograph [works out? unclear].
que a fotografia trabalha.
One of them, you see, is another journalist who is a realized soul.
Um deles é um outro jornalista que é uma alma realizada.
REPORTER: Oh I see. It’s the question of, You know,
Entendo. É uma questão de...
making people see, isn’t it starting I suppose once....
fazer as pessoas verem, não é? Começando, suponho, uma vez...
SHRI MATAJI: I think, I think so. Otherwise [unclear].
Eu acho, Eu acho. Senão (…)
REPORTER: [unclear]
Repórter: (…)
SHRI MATAJI: [Unclear] responsibility
(…) responsabilidade.
[unclear] for everyone.
(…) por todos.
REPORTER: [unclear] SHRI MATAJI: Isn’t it?
- Repórter: (…) - Não é?
After all, newspaper should give some good news also.
Afinal, os jornais devem dar algumas novas notícias boas também.
May God bless you.
Que Deus o abençoe.
[unclear]. You are [unclear]. It’s all right.
(…). Você é (…). Tudo bem.
All right. It was very beautiful.
Tudo bem. Foi muito belo.
We can give this address. Will you please?
Nós podemos dar este endereço. Por favor, você poderia?
And you tell them about [unclear].
E falar com eles sobre (…).
Tell them about [unclear]. [Can you ... unclear] ?
Falar com eles sobre (…). [Você pode (…)]?
[unclear Douglas is genius?].
[(…) Douglas é gênio?]
I want [unclear] anyway, he wants to [unclear].
Eu quero (…) de qualquer maneira, ele quer (…).
He’s a genius. He’s a genius.
Ele é um gênio. Ele é um gênio.
It's the truth.
É verdade.
He got into speed and I also got to got into speed with him,
Ele se apressou e também teve de se apressar com ele,
I said, “Let Me talk fast.”
Eu disse: “Deixe-Me falar rápido.”
All right? Now, thank you for the cameraman.
Tudo bem? Agora, obrigada pelo cameraman.
“This team follows You”, he said come.
“Essa equipe segue a Senhora”, ele disse: “Venham”.